

PH.D. STUDENT AT THE UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTO

Paul Allen Center, 185 E Stevens Way NE AE100R, Seattle, WA 98195

Summary_

Research Manifold learning, Geometric data analysis, Dynamic networks, Embedding.

Publications First author of 2 top-tier Machine Learning conference (NeurIPS, KDD) papers and 1 NeurIPS workshop poster.

Affiliations Institute for Pure and Applied Mathematics, Microsoft Corporation, University of Washington, National Taiwan University.

Programming Python (Advanced), MATLAB (Advanced), JavaScript (Intermediate), C++ (Intermediate).

Languages English (Professional), Mandarin (Native), Taiwanese (Native).

Education

University of Washington

Seattle, WA
Sep. 2016 - PRESENT

Ph.D. IN ELECTRICAL ENGINEERING

National Taiwan University

Taipei, Taiwan

B.S. IN PHYSICS

Sep. 2011 - Jun. 2015

Publications

· Advisor: Marina Meilă

REFERRED PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **YU-CHIA CHEN** and Marina Meilă. Selecting the independent coordinates of manifolds with large aspect ratios. In *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 32*, pages 1086–1095, 2019
- [2] Samson J. Koelle, Hanyu Zhang, Marina Meilă and **Yu-Chia Chen**. Manifold Coordinates with Physical Meaning. *Second Workshop on Machine Learning and the Physical Sciences (NeurIPS 2019)*, Vancouver, Canada, December, 2019
- [3] **YU-CHIA CHEN**, Avleen S. Bijral, and Juan Lavista Ferres. On Dynamic Network Models and Application to Causal Impact. In *Proceedings of the 25th ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery & Data Mining*, KDD '19, pages 1194–1204, New York, NY, USA, 2019. ACM
- [4] **YU-CHIA CHEN**, Dominique Perrault-Joncas, Marina Meilă, and James McQueen. Improved Graph Laplacian via Geometric Self-Consistency. *NIPS Workshop on NIPS Highlights (MLTrain), Learn How to code a paper with state of the art frameworks*, Long Beach, CA, December 2017
- [5] Peifeng Jing, Kosuke Winston, **Yu-Chia Chen**, Benjamin S. Freedman, and Lih Y. Lin. Patterning and Colonizing Stem Cells with Optical Trapping. In *Optics in the Life Sciences Congress (2017), Paper OtM4E.2*, page OtM4E.2. Optical Society of America, April 2017
- [6] **YU-CHIA CHEN**, Cih-Su Wang, Tsung-Yuan Chang, Tai-Yuan Lin, Hsiu-Mei Lin, and Yang-Fang Chen. Ultraviolet and visible random lasers assisted by diatom frustules. *Optics Express*, 23(12):16224–16231, June 2015
- [7] Cih-Su Wang, Chi-Shung Liau, Tzu-Ming Sun, **Yu-Chia Chen**, Tai-Yuan Lin, and Yang-Fang Chen. Biologically inspired band-edge laser action from semiconductor with dipole-forbidden band-gap transition. *Scientific Reports*, 5:8965, March 2015

PREPRINTS & WORKS IN PREPARATION

- [8] **YU-CHIA CHEN**, James McQueen, Samson J. Koelle, Marina Meilă, Stefan Chmiela and Alexandre Tkatchenko. Modern Manifold Learning Methods for MD data a step by step procedural overview.
- [9] Samson J. Koelle, Hanyu Zhang, Marina Meilă and Yu-CHIA CHEN. Manifold Coordinates with Physical Meaning. (Submitted to JMLR)

Experience _____

Geometric Data Analysis Group (prof. Marina Meilă), University of Washington

Seattle, WA

Ph.D. Student Researcher

Apr. 2017 - PRESENT

- Selecting the independent coordinates of manifolds with large aspect ratios.
 - Efficient criterion based subset selection algorithm for finding independent coordinates that produce smooth embedding.
 - Paper [1] accepted to NeurIPS 2019 (acceptance rate 21.2%).
- Fast random projection based graph Laplacian construction algorithm for large scale manifold learning.
- Manifold learning for molecular dynamics (MD) simulation data [8].

Microsoft Research Redmond, WA

RESEARCH INTERN Jun. 2018 - Sep. 2018

- Studied large scale dynamic network model based on stochastic block model (SBM) and the extension to causal impact on temporal graphs.
- Paper [3] accepted to KDD 2019 research track (acceptance rate 14.2%).

Psychological Warfare Group, Ministry of National Defense

Taipei, Taiwan Aug. 2015 - Jul. 2016

FRONT-END SOFTWARE ENGINEER (COMPULSORY MILITARY SERVICE)

- Lead engineer on cloud-based file exchanging platform, which enabled user to search, view and share streaming media.
- Technology used: JavaScript (react.js), HMTL/CSS.

Semiconductor Laboratory (prof. Yang-Fang Chen), National Taiwan University

Taipei, Taiwan

Undergraduate Researcher

Feb. 2014 - Jun. 2015

- Investigated bio-photonics devices with wide spectrum range [6].
- Studied Perovskite and CdTe core shell quantum dots assisted random laser in bio-inspired materials [7].

Other Experience & Course Projects_

Institute for Pure & Applied Mathematics (IPAM), UCLA

Los Angeles, CA

VISITING RESEARCHER

Sep. 2019 - Dec. 2019

• Participant of the Machine Learning for Physics and the Physics of Learning long program.

Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering, University of Washington

Seattle, WA

TEACHING ASSISTANT

Jan. 2017 - Dec. 2017

• Courses: Digital Signal Processing (graduate level), Devices And Circuits, Discrete Time Linear Systems, Fundamentals of Electrical Engineering.

Selfie Sensei: Convolutional Neural Network based selfie instructor

Seattle, WA

Course Project

Apr. 2017 - Jun 2017

• Built and trained the Google Inception-v3 model on 40 thousand selfies collected from twitter with hashtag #selfie.

Large scale medical subject heading (MeSH) term indexing

Seattle, WA

COURSE PROJECT

Jan. 2017 - Mar. 2017

• Built a CNN trained with skipgram word2vec embedding to annotate 27k MeSH terms on 12M academic articles.

Photonics Lab, University of Washington

Seattle, WA

GRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANT

Sep. 2016 - Dec. 2016

• Investigated high accuracy mass sensing using Nanostructure-enhanced laser tweezers and its application to stem cell patterning [5].

ScoreMaster Team Taipei, Taiwan

Co-founder

Dec. 2013 - Aug. 2014

• Developed online tutoring platform that matched high school students and undergraduate tutors.

Honors & Awards ____

2019	Student Travel Award, NeurIPS 2019	Vancouver, Canada
2019	Student Travel Award, KDD 2019	Anchorage, AK
2019	Travel Grant, UW Department of Electrical & Computer Engineering	Seattle, WA
2013	Scholarship, Taipower Academic Scholarship	Taipei, Taiwan
2012	Scholarship, Taipower Academic Scholarship	Taipei, Taiwan
2010	Second prizes, Physics Scholastic Ability Contest	Kaohsiung, Taiwan

Selected Talks_____

Dec. 2019 Poster Presentation , NeurIPS'19, Selecting the Independent Coordinates of Manifolds with Large Aspect Ratios.	Vancouver, Canada
Oct. 2019 Seminar Talk , IPAM, Selecting the Independent Coordinates of Manifolds with Large Aspect Ratios.	Los Angeles, CA
Aug. 2019 Poster Presentation , KDD'19, On Dynamic Network Models and Application to Causal Impact.	Anchorage, AK
Sep. 2018 Seminar Talk , Microsoft, On Dynamic Network Models and Application to Causal Impact.	Redmond, WA
Jan. 2018 Seminar Talk , UW Geometric Data Analysis Group, <i>Improved Graph Laplacian via geometric self-consistency</i> .	Seattle, WA



UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON

CSE 525 Randomized Algorithm; EE 546 Learning and Game Theory; STAT 512 Statistical Inference; STAT 548 Machine Learning for Big Data; STAT 538 Statistical Learning; CSE 599 Interplay between Convex Optimization and Geometry; MATH 515 Fundamental of Optimization; EE 576 Computer Vision; EE 595 Data Science for Sequencing; CSE 517 Natural Language Processing; EE 518 Digital Signal Processing.

NATIONAL TAIWAN UNIVERSITY (SELECTED)

PHYS 8049 Introduction to Quantum Computation & Information; PHYS 4001 Optics; PHYS 3002 Group Theory; PHYS 3001 Complex Analysis.

References_

Marina Meilă

DEPARTMENT OF STATISTICS. UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON

mmp@stat.washington.edu

Avleen S. Bijral

MICROSOFT CORPORATION

avbijral@microsoft.com

Les Atlas

DEPARTMENT OF ELECTRICAL & COMPUTER ENGINEERING, UNIVERSITY OF WASHINGTON

atlas@u.washington.edu

Yang-Fang Chen

DEPARTMENT OF PHYSICS, NATIONAL TAIWAN UNIVERSITY

yfchen@phys.ntu.edu.tw